Guide to the John Tabor Kempe Papers 1678-1782 (bulk 1752-1774) MS 344
New-York Historical Society
John Tabor Kempe Papers
1678-1782 (bulk 1752-1774)
New-York Historical Society
MS 344
7.5 Linear feet
The John Tabor Kempe Papers contain primarily court case records (12 boxes) for the colonial province of New York during the tenures of Attorneys General William Kempe and his son, John Tabor Kempe. The bulk of these records date from 1752 to 1774, and concern civil disputes, often over land ownership, tenancy and estates, as well as criminal acts. Also included in the papers are professional correspondences of both John Tabor Kempe and William Kempe, court agendas and fees, legal papers, land and property records, financial records, government documents, and a photograph.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Separated Materials
BV NYS -- Boundaries -- Oblong; two boxes of papers pertaining to the Oblong dispute.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The Alexander Papers, 1668-1818 (bulk 1717-1786), which also contain colonial court records.
Arrangement
The John Tabor Kempe Papers are organized into the following seven series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Court Case Records, 1678-1778 (bulk 1752-1774), and Undated
Series 2: Correspondence, 1730-1775 (bulk 1753-1774), and Undated
Series 3: Legal Papers, 1760-1782 and Undated
Series 4: Land and Property Records, 1742-1775 and Undated
Series 5: Financial Records, 1718-1775 and Undated
Series 6: Government Records, 1722-1773 and Undated
Series 7: Photograph, Undated
Scope and Contents note
The John Tabor Kempe Papers contain primarily court case records (12 boxes) for the colonial province of New York during the tenures of Attorneys General William Kempe and his son, John Tabor Kempe. The bulk of these records date from 1752 to 1774, and concern civil disputes, often over land ownership, tenancy and estates, as well as criminal acts. Offenses range from minor assaults and infractions to capital crimes, including murder and high treason. A separate database exists for the court case records in this collection, containing over 750 entries.
Also included in the papers are professional correspondences of both John Tabor and William Kempe, court agendas and fees, legal papers, land and property records, financial records, government documents, and a photograph.
While a number of well-known legal cases are represented in this collection (i.e. The King vs. Alexander McDougall), the John Tabor Kempe Papers also support research in the lives of ordinary colonial New Yorkers, many of whom are otherwise undocumented. Records also detail numerous land conflicts that erupted in the decades prior to the Revolutionary War, including riots and intrusion cases in the counties, and territorial disputes with Native Americans and with neighboring colonies, especially Connecticut and New Hampshire. Historians of colonial law will find a variety of cases and legal documents in this collection, and John Tabor Kempe's trial notes and correspondence provide insight into a prominent eighteenth-century legal mind.
This collection contains mostly professional records, with very little personal material for either John Tabor Kempe or William Kempe.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1752 Nov. William Kempe appointed Attorney General for the Province of New York
1759 July/Aug. William Kempe dies; his son, John Tabor Kempe, is appointed Attorney General for the Province of New York
1766 John Tabor Kempe marries Grace Coxe
1767 John Tabor Kempe travels to England; James Duane serves as acting Attorney General in his absence
1768 John Tabor Kempe resumes position, is re-appointed
1777 John Tabor Kempe's tenure as Attorney General ends
1783 John Tabor Kempe returns to England, makes Loyalist land claims
1791 John Tabor Kempe dies in England
Petitions.; Memorandums.; Subpoenas; Wills.; Assault and battery -- New York (State).; Indians Of North America -- Land tenure -- New York (State) -- Dutchess County.; Extinguishment of Indian title -- New York (State) -- Dutchess County.; Ejectment -- New York (State).; Correspondence.; Decedents' estates -- New York (State); Courts -- New York (State); Courts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Counterfeits and counterfeiting -- New York (State).; Costs (Law) -- New York (State).; Attorneys general; Jews -- New York (State) -- New York.; Justice, Administration of -- New York (State).; Affidavits.; Landlord and tenant -- New York (State); Larceny -- New York (State).; Deeds.; Lawyers -- Fees -- New York (State); Lawyers; Law -- New York (State).; Practice of law -- New York (State); Murder -- New York (State).; Libel and slander -- New York (State).; Rape -- New York (State); Prostitution -- New York (State).; Prisoners -- New York (State).; Real property -- New York (State); Trading with the enemy; Riots -- New York (State).; Treason -- New York (State).; Trials -- New York (State).; Trespass -- New York (State).; Trover and conversion -- New York (State).; Wappinger Indians; New York (State) -- Boundaries -- New Hampshire.; New Hampshire -- Boundaries -- New York (State).; New York (State) -- Boundaries.; New York (State) -- History -- French and Indian War, 1755-1763.; New York (State) -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; Oblong Tract (N.Y.); Accounts.; Bonds (legal records).; Briefs (legal documents); Criminal court records; Legal instruments; Civil court records; Daguerreotypes (photographs); Depositions.; Estate records.; Legal correspondence.; Land grants; Legal documents.; Legal notices; Bradstreet, John, 1711-1774; Bleecker, Rutger, 1745-1787; Chase, Henry, active 1760s-1770s; Cock, Ann; Cockburn, Will; Duncan, John; Dysart, Richard; Gomez, Daniel; Hausbrouck, Abraham; Hays, Solomon; Hayward, Sarah; Hicks, Whitehead, 1728-1780; Johnson, William, 1715-1774; Kempe, William, -1759; Klock, George; Lydius, John Henry, 1694-1791; Nimham, Daniel; Schuyler, Harmanus; Silvester, Peter; Spencer, George; Swords, Thomas; Wetherhead, John; Yates, Abraham, 1724-1796; Congregation Shearith Israel (New York, N.Y.); New York (State). Attorney General's Office; New York (State). Court of Oyer and Terminer (New York County); New York (State). Court of Vice Admiralty; New York (State). Supreme Court; New York (State). Court of General Sessions of the Peace (New York County); New York (State). Mayor's Court (New York)
- Series 1: Court Case Records, 1678-1778 (bulk 1752-1774), and Undated, 1678-1778 and Undated
  Scope and Contents
  The bulk of the court case records in this collection are for cases argued in the New York Supreme Court of Judicature. Other courts include the Court of Chancery, Court of Vice-Admiralty, New York General Sessions (in counties), New York General Quarter Sessions (in New York City), Court of Mayor and Aldermen, and the Court of Oyer and Terminer. Cases argued before the Governor and Council are also found in this series.
  Court case records are arranged by the court in which a case was argued. Within each court, cases are divided into criminal and civil, then arranged alphabetically by defendant for criminal cases, by plaintiff for civil cases. Cases with multiple plaintiffs or defendants are filed under the first name to appear on the documents. In addition, this series includes documents for cases for which the court, plaintiff or defendant cannot be determined. Cases where the court venue is unclear, but plaintiff and defendant are evident, are filed under "Court Undetermined." Documents that are most likely related to a court case, but the court, plaintiff, and/or defendant cannot be determined are filed under "Case Undetermined." Many of these undetermined cases are represented by a single document.
  Court case documents include briefs, presentments, affidavits, trial notes, complaints, statements of cases, indictments, memoranda, subpoenas, pleas, notices, depositions, rules, certiorari, narratios, replications, bail notices, trial notices, notes, petitions, jury lists, costs, and other relevant documents such as estate records or accounts. Many items are drafts or contemporary copies. Petitions not linked to any specific case are filed together within Case Undetermined.
  All cases in this series have been entered into a separate database. The database information generally includes court, location, dates, items, plaintiff and defendant, and charge or suit for each case. A notes field also contains other pertinent information about the case, such as references to other relevant cases and correspondence. (Correspondence that was filed with individual court cases has been removed to Series II, and each item removed is listed in the notes field--additional correspondence not listed may also relate to specific court cases, as many letters were already filed separately). A complete report derived from this database is available for researchers, sorted by court. A separate report sorted by charge/suit is also available. The database can be searched by name or keyword--see Manuscript Department staff.
  Court cases in the John Tabor Kempe Papers involve assault, debt, grand and petit larceny, riot, ejectment, keeping disorderly or bawdy houses, murder, estate disputes, libel, slander, trading with the enemy, trespass, rape, and counterfeiting, among other charges. The bulk of these cases occurred in New York City, though a number of major cases, especially land disputes, took place upstate. These include riots during the 1760s in Cortlandt Manor, Westchester Co. (King vs. Daniel Cornell et al, in the Supreme Court of Judicature), and Dutchess Co. (King vs. John Kane, King vs. Elisha Cole, both in Court of Oyer and Terminer; King vs. James Higby et al, in the Supreme Court of Judicature). Other prominent land disputes include Intrusion on Crown Lands cases in Albany Co. (King vs. John Henry Lydius, King vs. George Klock, King vs. John Van Rensselaer, all in the Supreme Court of Judicature) and the Wappinger Indian land claim led by Chief Daniel Nimham, argued before the Governor and Council.
  This collection also includes numerous land tenant ejectment cases. These suits were brought on the behalf of a fictitious current tenant, usually called "James Jackson," though other names were also used ("Peter Quiet," "John Denn"). Therefore, ejectment cases are filed by the first plaintiff to follow the fictitious name. The false names "John Stiles" and "John Turnout" were commonly used for defendants.
  Political cases represented in this series include King vs. Alexander McDougall in the Supreme Court of Judicature for libel/slander, several trading with the enemy cases during the French and Indian War (especially the various George Spencer cases in the Supreme Court of Judicature and the Court of Vice-Admiralty), and a number of cases involving maladministration of Justices of the Peace.
  Court case records also document the quotidian disputes of New Yorkers, particularly in assault cases, and sometimes reveal contentious relationships between men and women, masters and servants, ministers and their congregations, and neighbors. Women are present throughout the series as both plaintiffs and defendants, and a few cases include unkept marriage promises, and accusations of rape. Many cases involve disputes within religious institutions, particularly the Protestant Dutch Church. The King vs. Nepthali Hart Meyers, Hayman Levi, Daniel Gomez et al in the Supreme Court of Judicature details a violent disagreement within a NYC synagogue.
  Several cases in this collection involve the accusation of slaves for various crimes; see King vs. Belinda, King vs. Venus, King vs. Falmouth, King vs. Pompey, in the Supreme Court of Judicature and King vs. Abraham, King vs. Scipio in Court Undetermined. A number of cases concern slaves seeking their freedom, often claiming false enslavement in the American colonies; see Juan Miranda vs. Cornelius and Sarah Van Ranst in the Supreme Court of Judicature, the case of Francis de Salas Cortilla in Governor and Council, and the cases of Vacan Beneto (petition), Simon Moore, Jacob Quaco, and the estate of William West, all in Case Undetermined.
  In some instances, the court in which a case was argued was determined through the use of an outside source, especially Julius Goebel Jr. and T. Raymond Naughton's Law Enforcement in Colonial New York: A Study in Criminal Procedure (1664-1776) (NY: The Commonwealth Fund, 1944). Daniel Allen Hearn's Legal Executions in New York State, 1639-1963 (N.C.: McFarland and Co., 1997) was also consulted. Both are referenced in the note field of the database when applicable. Further information on many cases in the collection can also be found in these sources.
  Note: Many cases contain alternate spellings for the names of plaintiffs and defendants. The most common was used for indexing; alternate spellings are also included in brackets. A number of documents contain the abbreviation "ads," i.e. John Smith ads. William Thomas. With this abbreviation, the defendant is listed first and the plaintiff listed second, rather than the more common Thomas vs. Smith, or Thomas agt. Smith. Other abbreviations found in the collection are "ex dem" meaning "upon the demise" (used in ejectment cases) and "qui tam" meaning the plaintiff has launched a civil suit on behalf of the state.
  - Subseries 1: Supreme Court of Judicature, Criminal
    - The King vs. The Mayor, Recorder & Alderman of the City of Albany, 1762 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Rule for return of mandamus (copy).
    - The King vs. Mary Allison, Ephraim Lockwood, Hendrick Sidam, David Robinson, Mary Mucklewain, John Christie, Mathew Woosey, Joheph Heginbotham, John Wilks, Jane Robinson, Ernest August Jacobus Printz Van Tollinsee with a hundred others: Riot, 1754 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The King vs. James Armstrong: Assault and Battery, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The King vs. Samuel Ashcraft and Thomas Norton, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Citation: court determined with Goebel and Naughton, Law Enforcement in Colonial New York.
    - The King vs. Theophilact Bache, 1765 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The King vs. John Barnes: Trespass and contempt, 1756 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The King vs. Levy Barnet: Grand larceny, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Theft from sloop Polly.
    - The King vs. Belinda: Murder, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Belinda, slave of William Cook, accused of the murder of Cooler, slave of Nathaniel Marston.
    - The King vs. Ambrose Bill, Magnus Burger, and John Scandlon: Extortion, 1774-1775 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The King vs. Catherine Branson [Ranson]: Grand Larceny, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Alias Hannah Harding. Presented on the same sheet as The King vs. William Johnson. See Legal Executions, 1767, listed as Bronson.
    - The King vs. James Brown: Receiving stolen goods, 1771 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Citation: court determined with Goebel & Naughton, Law Enforcement in Colonial New York.
    - The King vs. John Burns: Debt, 1771 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Case also involves Paul and John Gallaudet.
    - The King vs. Joshua Bishop, William Pendergast [Prendergast], Augustine Rogers, Isaac Wright, Jonathan Wright, William Wright, Bartlet Brundege, John Bishop, Joseph Tidd, Joseph Tidd Jr., Solomon Tidd, Daniel Cornell, Richard Cornell, William Cornell, and Isaac Gonon: Riot, April 1766 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Trial in Westchester County and pertains to a riot in Cortlandt Manor. There are four cases filed together which include information and lists of rioters in each case.
    - The King vs. Joshua Bishop, Isaac Wright, and Daniel Brundege: Riot at Cortlandt Manor, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The King vs. Hester Campbell [Cammel], Margaret Waters, Catherine Johnson, Thomas Fraser [Frasure], Robert Burril [Burrill], and Barbery [Barberie] Myer: Keeping disorderly bawdy house, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      See also The King vs. Catherine Johnson and The King vs. Barbery [Barberie] Myer in Supreme Court of Judicature.
    - The King vs. Robert Campbell, Archibald Livingston, and Alexander Coleman: Riotous assembly, 1764-1768 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Orange County
    - The King vs. John Cannon: Assault and battery, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The King vs. Catherine Carroe [Carrae]: Keeping disorderly bawdy house, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The King vs. William Chase [Chace]: Assault, 1761 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      See also Leake vs. Chase and Scott vs. Chase.
    - The King vs. Elizabeth Clark [alias Elizabeth Johnson]: Larceny, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Two seperate cases.
    - The King vs. George Clark and James McKinney, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Attack on William Thorn.
    - The King vs. Thomas Clay, Jacob Osborn, and John Gallway: Burglary, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The King vs. John Coe, Paulus VanderVort, Nehemiah Seamans, Jacob Vanderbilt, Gysbert Cuyper, Tounis Cuyper, Cornelius Cuyper, Joseph Allison, Benjamin Allison, Henry Halstead, and Nicholas Coneklin: Trespass, 1760 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The King vs. Mary Connor [Conner]: Keeping a disorderly bawdy house, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Case includes a presentment.
    - The King vs. Daniel Cornell [Cornel], Isaac Wright, Joshua Bishop, Richard Cornell, Joseph Tidd, and Daniel Chapman: Riot, 1766 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Riot in Cortlandt Manor. Four cases, filed together with lists of rioters in each case.
    - The King vs. Daniel Cornell, Isaac Wright, Joshua Bishop, Richard Cornell, Joseph Tidd, Daniel Chapman, Edward Gonon, John Cross, Jesse Harris, James Barker, Richard Satterley, Nathan Brundege, John Quitterfield, Robert Wright, William Cornell, and William Derbyshire: Riot, April 1766 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The King vs. John Coats, Archibald Campbell, John Campbell, William Campbell, Adam McKain alias Simmons and persons unknown: Breaking and entering, 1766 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The King vs. William Cockrain, William Coventry, and Alexander Patterson: Murder, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Albany County; Murder of Jacobus Van Allen.
    - The King vs. Waddel Cunningham, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The King vs. Waddel Cunningham and Thomas White: Trading with the enemy, 1762-1764 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Also informed against: Godardus Van Solingen, Thomas Livingston, Thomas Smith, Philip Smith, Theunis Thew, William Williams, William Dobbs, Jacob Van Zandt, George Moore, John Keating, Abraham Lott, James Bell, John Fox. Also involved: John Audebon
    - The King vs. Abraham Slutt, Thomas Baxter, and William Finch: Riot, July 1766 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The King vs. Mary Daily [Dailey] [Dalley]: Larceny, 1769-1771 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Four different cases involving larceny. Listed as Dailey on the list of Legal Executions, 1771.
    - The King vs. John Dalton: Murder, 1765-1766 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Murder of John Moschalek [Marschalk] [Marschalck] [Morschalk] [Moschalck]. Witnesses: Mary Moschalek, John Wharton, John Dunn, Martin Lawless. Affidavits of Lawless, Dunn, James Kelly, John Williamson. Docs signed by Thomas Shreve, coroner.
    - The King vs. Roper Dawson: Murder, 1765-1766 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Murder of John McKenzie.
    - The King vs. Peter De Witt: Assault, 1763 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Dutchess County; also Adam Barrack. See letter from Barrack to John Tabor Kempe dated March 7, 1764.
    - The King vs. Elizabeth Dent: Larceny, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Pickpocket incident, victim Jeremiah Brewer.
    - The King vs. Andrew Darcus: Larceny, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The King vs. John Domine: Assault and attempted rape, 1766 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Depositions of Catherine Larking and Mary Clarkson. Charges of assault and attempted rape of Catherine Larking, age 8.
    - The King vs. John Dowers: Trespass and keeping a disorderly bawdy house, 1764-1768 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Two or three cases. Also against Elizabeth Dowers. On the same bill as The King vs. Dalton, 1765.
    - The King vs. John Driskill: Assault, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Assault on Thomas Lloyd.
    - The King vs. Mathew DuBois, Lawrence Van Klock, Nicholas DeLaVergne, Henry Vanderburgh, Abraham Bokee, James Smith, Roswell Hopkins, William Doughty, Cornelius Luyster, Daniel Castle, Jacobus Terbos, James Duncan, Timothy Soule, Samuel Peters, and Anthony Yeherton: Maladministration as Justice of the Peace, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Dutchess County; two cases.
    - The King vs. Jane Dun [Dunn]: Bigamy, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Witnesses include Thomas Dun, Samuel Acmudey, and Joseph Treat.
    - The King vs. Samuel Dunscomb, 1754 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Notice of trial on same sheet and filed with The King vs. John Livingston, Supreme Court of Judicature.
    - The King vs. Jacob Dyckman, Lawrence Cortright, and William Glenston, 1754 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The King vs. Sarah Dyllon: Keeping disorderly bawdy house, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      On same parchment as King vs. Ann Hortwyck in Supreme Court of Judicature.
    - The King vs. Ann Hortwyck: Keeping disorderly bawdy house, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      On same presentment as King vs. Sarah Dyllon.
    - The King vs. Cornelius Edison, John Crawford, John Brown, and Eneus: Petit larceny, 1771 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Presentment for breaking and entering the house of Theophilact Bache. Eneus was a slave of Mary Ellison.
    - The King vs. William Elkins and Abraham Stokes: Larceny, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. Alexander Ennis: Assault and battery, 1762 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. Margaret Erwin [Ervin]: Petit larceny, 1771 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. Falmouth: Murder, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Falmouth, slave of Robert Gibbs, was tried for the attempted murder of Jane Gibb. Listed on the same sheet as King vs. James Reed.
    - The King vs. Philip Fell: Larceny, 1765-1766 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. James Ferguson, 1761 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. James Ferguson et al., Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. Benjamin Ferris, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Westchester County
    - The King vs. Gilbert Ferris: Attempted murder, 1749-1755 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Accused of attempting to murder his wife, Hannah, by poisoning.
    - The King vs. James and Jane Fielding: Keeping disorderly bawdy house, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      On the same sheet as The King vs. James Long
    - The King vs. Eleanor Flood and Sybrant G. Van Schaick, 1760-1764 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. Thomas Flood: Breaking and entering, 1763 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      See also a letter to James Tabor Kempe from Thomas Flood dated April 29, 1763.
    - The King vs. George Folliott: Debt, 1761-1763 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Case includes narratio, deumurrer, and joinder in demurrer.
    - The King vs. Alexander and Susannah Forbes: Robbery and petit larceny, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Deposition of Margaret Brown.
    - The King vs. John Franklin et al.: Riot and assault, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Riot and assault against John Jones, tarred and feathered.
    - The King vs. George and Abby Garlin: Assault, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. Sarah Gillet: Grand larceny, 1767-1768 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes two cases.
    - The King vs. William Gillet: Receiving stolen goods and keeping a disorderly bawdy house, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. William Gilliland: Counterfeiting, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. Daniel Gomez: Assault, 1766 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. John Gooding: Assault on a constable, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      On the same presentment as The King vs. Falmouth. Case includes presentment.
    - The King vs. Ennis Graham, 1762 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. Edward Grant: Grand larceny, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The King vs. Charles Green, John Rundle, and George Dibble: Riot and obstructing survey, 1762-1763 (Box 1, Folder 4)